שבוע טוב *Shavua tov*, today’s דף Daf *daf* is כ"ד *chaf dalet*
in סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*. We pick up at the very bottom of
כ"ג *chaf gimmel* עמוד ב *amud bet*. We’ve just been dealing with
these interesting reflections or debates around first of all teaching your daughter
תורה Torah *Torah*, לימדה תפלות Tiflus *limda tiflus*, or you have to
in order so she understands how the world works, which was preceded
by a whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* about the value
of תלמוד תורה talmud torah. *Talmud Torah* for women. So the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* got to it indirectly, asking what type of זכות zchus
*zechus* is תולה *toleh* for women. But it was very interesting in
this type of a context about the woman’s role as like an
אינה מצווה ועושה *eina metzuvah ve’osah* and so on. And then the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* got onto, I’ll go back and say what about
that, but then got onto the statement about רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
*Rabbi Yehoshua* about being skeptical about women who appear to be looking,
trying to be like aesthetic פרישות *perishut*, like separate themselves from physical
pleasures, saying that women are always trying to sort of seek sexual
opportunity, also very interesting in the context of סוטה Sotah *Sotah*, and
then talking about other people that are not whom they seem. So
let me just say a quick word about the תפלות *tiflus* issue
before going on. Obviously that’s a whole long discussion in itself, but
as might not be surprising,
you know, there are
obviously there are communities, for a long time women were not educated
just because women weren’t educated in general in general society, and it
did not have to emerge from any type of particular religious conviction,
but nevertheless, it certainly, you know, in the modern era when women’s
education was definitely an issue and a possibility and an opportunity, the
question around women learning תורה Torah *Torah* and specifically like תורה שבעל
פה Torah SheBaal Peh *Torah Sheba’al Peh*, you know, really sort of,
you know, became for some a very ideologically, ideological, halachic, religious position
that women can’t do and based on this whole idea of תפלות
*tiflus*, and for others like the הרב *Rav* and the לובביץ'ר רבי
Rebbe *Lubavitcher Rebbe* and so on became something that is absolutely essential
for women to do. So as far as, so a lot of
that has far more to do with
broader sort of sociological religious issues than the specific question of the
interpretation of the issue in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* of כאילו לימדה
תפלות *ke’ilu limda tiflus*. As we actually saw the תוספות Tosfot *Tosfos*
quotes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi*
where רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* had a, you know, not
just a concern about using this as a, as a means for
to get around the laws of סוטה *Sotah*, but he had a
very harsh position on the, on the value of women learning תורה
Torah *Torah* altogether, מוטב ישרפו דברי תורה Torah ואל ימסרו לנשים *mutav
yisrefu divrei Torah ve’al yimsru lenashim*.
So again, coming maybe from a sense about women as frivolous or
women, you know, whatever his attitude was towards women, that there was
something that was, that was really terribly pernicious and destructive about women
learning תורה Torah *Torah*. But I’m not, so anyway, the point is
that
these differences are probably have a lot more to do with, as
I said, broader sort of sociological religious issues, attitudes towards women, women’s
roles in society, attitudes towards larger society and so on. As far
as it relates to the specific issues in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*,
a number of points have been made, have been pointed out. Number
one is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn’t come down on one particular
side of whether of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer* versus בן
עזאי *Ben Azzai*. Number two is, so you know, question, who do
we פוסקין *pasken* like, assuming it’s a matter of פסק *psak* altogether,
let alone a question about just sort of some type of religious,
you know, advice and direction. Number two is רמב"ם *Rambam* quotes רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* but he does not quote it as
פסק *psak*. The רמב"ם *Rambam* says, you know, anybody should can learn
תורה Torah, *Torah* and a woman can learn תורה Torah *Torah* and
she’s like אינה מצווה ועושה *eina metzuvah ve’osah*, that type of a
framing like we had in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but nevertheless the
רמב"ם *Rambam* says יש לה שכר sachar *yesh lah s'char*. אבל אמרו
חכמים *Aval amru chachamim*,
you know, כל המלמד בתו תורה Kol Hamelamed Bitto Torah כאילו לימדה
תפלות *kol hamelamed bito Torah ke’ilu limdah tiflus*. So אבל אמרו חכמים
*aval amru chachamim* means he’s not seeing this as הלכה Halacha, *halachah*,
he’s seeing this as a type of a, you know, advice, religious
direction,
and the whole other discussion about רמב"ם *Rambam*’s attitude towards women and
their intellectual abilities and so on. But number one is it’s certainly
not being framed as a הלכה Halacha *halachah*. Number two is the
issue about some want to emphasize the point of כל המלמד בתו
תורה Torah. *kol hamelamed bito Torah*, you know, about a question about
whether it’s like a single person’s decision, you know, whether it’s a
broader communal type of a thing, maybe want to sort of make
something out of that. But you know, and the, but the bigger
issue that really comes up is, you know, how much is that
contextual? How much is that in a time when women are not
educated and, you know, and were not maybe for the most part
able to handle, you know, if you wanted to sort of say,
even within רבי Rebbe אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, you know, let alone that
there’s an opposing position, you know, in a, in certain circumstances in
which they were not able to handle, you know, they did not
have this type of academic, intellectual training, so therefore that type of
a statement like could be made. So on the one hand that’s
a negative approach... emerges from a particular historical sociological perspective, and number
two, the question is what are the sort of opposite factors in
today's society, and that of course is very strong arguments that are
made about the consequences of not learning when they are pursuing other
intellectual fields
is very grave. So anyway, bottom line is
that was
a lot of the battleground might come up about the how do
you interpret this one line, but the issues really
are much, much broader than this exact question about this. But in
terms of the, in the exact it's not like they emerge from,
the reason there are different opinions about women learning is because people
have different interpretations of this line of רבי אליעזר. No, it works
a little bit in the opposite direction. Okay, but if you want
to know about the actual ways in which this line is interpreted,
I mean and the questions about how much I see רבי אליעזר's
position as sort of weighty in terms of הלכה, Halacha I would
say number one, question, is this a matter of הלכה Halacha at
all or about פסקנאינג paskening it at all or just different opinions
like in different אגדתות Aggadotahs or whatever. Number two, even within
רבי אליעזר, so that's number one, and is there a question, is
there an issue who we פסקן pasken like, is there an idea
of do we פסקן pasken this way, פסקן pasken that way. Number
two is how much is רבי אליעזר saying הלכה Halacha at all.
And number three is how much was his statement shaped by particular
realities relating to women at that time? And the flip side of
that is number four is how much our contemporary realities demand a
very different type of response and it would be very destructive, it
would be very counterproductive to be following this type of an approach
in today's society. So anyway, that's a very בקיצור b'kitzer type of
a שיעור shiur on that. Moving on, let's get back to the
גמרא. Gemara's Okay, I knew I shouldn't have gone down that path.
Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara
is dealing with the issue of what do you call it, see
I shouldn't listen to you Micah. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is dealing
with the issue about who is a, about other people who don't
present necessarily as who they are. So you had רבי יהושע's Rabbi
Yehoshua idea about a, so it's about women who seem to want
to act as if they're not interested in sexual pleasure or whatever,
but it's really a farce. And the other thing he mentioned was
the חסיד שוטה, chassid shoteh, which is somebody actually who, it's not
a question about presenting as who they're not, but they don't really
understand what they're taking on the externals of חסידות, chassidut, but they
in a way don't understand what real righteousness is.
Right, yeah, well not just priorities, I think it's more about being
drawn after the externals and not understanding the essence. I think that's
a lot of what this is, externals versus the reality. So here's
somebody who doesn't understand what the essence of true חסידות chassidut is.
And then you had the person who was the רשע ערום, rasha
arum, who was the deceptive wicked person, so they don't appear wicked,
but they're doing it because they're very scheming. So anyway, we pick
up with this bottom of כ"א עמוד ב', kaf-aleph amud bet, and
it's the following. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, so we're still
giving a list of who's a רשע ערום. rasha arum. זה מחטיא
אחרים באורחותיו. Zeh machtiya acherim b'orchotav.
This is somebody who tips people into his, towards his path. So
what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says it means ראו ועשו
כמוני לכו בדרכי. Reu v'asu kamoni l'chu b'drachai.
Look, I'm setting a good example, follow me. לא נתכוון זה להראות
עצמו כחסיד בעיני הבריות ואין תוכו כבראו. Lo nitkaven zeh l'harot atzmo
k'chassid b'einei habriyot v'ein tocho k'baro.
You're appearing very righteous and you're telling people follow your example, but
you're really just doing that because you want to set yourself up
as righteous so people don't really start suspecting what your real sort
of wicked stuff is that you're doing that nobody sees. It doesn't
exactly fit the language in the גמרא. Gemara. תוספות Tosafot says I
think more convincingly that basically is you give people advice that ultimately
helps out your interests and are not necessarily in their best interest,
okay? So somebody's asking your advice: 'Should I buy this car or
not buy this car? Should I invest here or there?' and you
give them advice because ultimately that's something that's going to help you
and you really don't have their interest in mind. Yeah, something לפני
עיוור.
lifnei iver.
Yeah, one of the לפני עיוור lifnei iver is exactly that. Why
is it why... yeah,
so we're not talking about what איסורים issurim people are עובר, over,
or if they're even עובר over on איסורים, issurim, we're talking about,
about certain types of people, of character traits and things to be
aware of. The type of a person who's going to present themselves
as always very altruistic and so on, but really everything is about
how it's serving them. You know, it's sort of like people have
these books out right like, the seven different personality types you have
to deal with at work,
and how to recognize them and deal with them. So this is
like you should recognize there are these types of people out there
that always appear very פרום frum but they got something else going
on. Okay, yeah, sometimes seven types.
You're right, רבי דובר, Rabbi Dover, for you we'll make an ace.
Okay, so okay. אמר רבי זריקא... Amar Rabbi Zrika... So okay אמר
רבי זריקא אמר רב הונא Amar Rabbi Zreika Amar Rav Huna זה
המיקל לעצמו ומחמיר לאחרים. Zeh HaMeikal LeAtzmo U'Machmir Le'Acheirim. This is somebody
that is lenient to themselves and מחמיר Machmir for other people. So
they're very פרום. Frum. You ask them what the הלכה Halacha is,
oh you're not allowed to do that on שבת, Shabbos, you know
whatever so they appear really very righteous you know every time you
ask them a שאלה Shaila always being very מחמיר Machmir but presumably
in a way that people aren't seeing they're always for themselves they're
always being very
מיקל. Meikal. Okay עולא אמר Ulla Amar זה שקרא ושנה ולא שימש
תלמידי חכמים. Zeh SheKara VeShana VeLo Shimish Talmidei Chachamim.
Somebody who learns and מקרא Mikra learns משנה Mishna but never actually
you know put in the time to attend to תורה Torah scholars
and really like you know and therefore what's the problem of ולא
שימש? VeLo Shimish? So רש"י Rashi says the problem of ולא שימש
VeLo Shimish is ללמוד סברת הגמרא בטעמי המשנה Lilmod Sevarat HaGemara BeTaamei
HaMishna
מהן. Mahen. So you know all the material but you don't really
know what it means. You never actually engaged yourself in the type
of the rabbinic discourse שאין תורתו על בוריה SheEin Torato Al Boryah
so that person doesn't deeply understand it ואין ללמוד הימנו VeEin Lilmod
Heimenno and you can't just learn from משנה Mishna straight שהרי על
ידי הטעמים יש חילוק באיסור והיתר בדיני ממונות לזכות ולחייב ובטהרה לטמא
ולטהר. Sheharei Al Yedei HaTaamim Yesh Chilluk BeIssur VeHeter BeDinei Mamonot LeZakot
ULeChayev UBeTahara LeTamei ULeTaher.
Only by understanding the reasons would you understand what's really going on
and how to apply it דגמרא מדקדקא DeGemara Medakdeka מאי טעמא אמר
הכי Mai Taama Amar Hachi מאי טעמא אמר הכי Mai Taama Amar
Hachi what's it based on ומאי בינייהו UMai Beineiyhu ואיכא בינייהו VeIka
Beineiyhu and when it's sort of all of that conceptual deep understanding
כך וכך. Kach VeKach. So why is he an ערום? Arum? Like
maybe he's being irresponsible and maybe he's being a רשע Rasha because
he's in the sense that he's sinning because he thinks he knows
the הלכה halakha but where is he being the schemer? וערום VeArum
it says הוא שמשמיע קולו ושונה משניותיו Hu SheMashmia Kolo VeShoneh Mishnayotav
כסבור הוא שבקי בטעמיהם Kasevar Hu SheBaki BeTaameihem ונוהגין בו כבוד כתלמידי
חכמים VeNohegin Bo Kavod KeTalmidei Chachamim
because he goes around he's very erudite. I think we all we
you know here's another here's a nice tie. We all know people
that are like very erudite you know and can quote a million
sources but they have no deep understanding. Right? So this guy actually
the גמרא Gemara has a word for that as well which isn't
exactly this point but the גמרא Gemara calls it a חמור נושא
ספרים. Chamor Nosei Sefarim. Somebody who basically is like a walking library,
they're a donkey who's carrying like all of these these books on
their back, all this information in their head but they don't have
really any like deep understanding. So anyway here's somebody that they're constantly
quoting משנה Mishna ופסוקים UPsukim etc. so everybody thinks oh this guy
is so knowledgeable etc. and they follow him but he actually doesn't
really understand it and doesn't know what to do. So again he's
more like he's more like irresponsible than a רשע. Rasha. Maybe he's
a רשע Rasha in sense of his not being responsible like he
doesn't want to put in the work to really understand it. Anyway
that's the way רש"י Rashi understands. I think you could also suggest
that ולא שימש תלמידי חכמים VeLo Shimish Talmidei Chachamim is not in
terms of gaining the proper intellectual understanding but gaining the proper sort
of character development. Right? The idea of שימוש Shimush is that you
learn how תורה Torah is really supposed to guide us and transform
our character and translate into the way the you know the small
ways in which we act and interact with other people. So somebody
who basically they're just interested in the knowledge and not really in
that personal investment also learn about what that work A the personal
investment of time to be משמש תלמידי חכמים Meshamesh Talmidei Chachamim and
B to understand what that you know how תורה Torah, has to
be working on our personality. Ultimately that's a type of like a
רשע ערום Rasha Arum you know that they're they're allowing themselves with
their you know with their natural more unrefined character traits but they're
doing all the stuff that makes them appear like a תלמיד חכם.
Talmid Chacham. Dov you had a question?
It sounds like kind of the חפץ חיים's Chafetz Chaim's idea of
the למדן Lamdan of the something.
Book learning is not the same.
רש"י Rashi you mean, not what I just said. What I said.
Oh well I was I was actually not talking about knowing the
איסור והיתר. Issur VeHeter. I was talking about the שימוש תלמידי חכמים
Shimush Talmidei Chachamim in terms of like learning learning like character traits,
like learning about what a true... not the חפץ חיים Chafetz Chaim
Soloveitchik numeric tradition is about is about action is about just you
know yeah.
But רש"י Rashi is that isn't that wasn't that the role of
of of certain people whose whose job it was just to memorize
things?
Right. So I guess for רש"י Rashi the point would be if
you know that... Right and the גמרא Gemara time.
Yeah. Right. I think I think that the point you're right like
if somebody understands no no I'm just the memorizer don't ask me
any הלכה halacha that's not a רשע ערום. Rasha Arum. I think
רש"י Rashi is saying it's a type of a person who because
of all their book knowledge believes themselves to be and presents themselves
to be like a real תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and somebody who
you know who can tell you what to do or knows himself
what to do. Yes.
Learning מקרא Mikra and משנה Mishna but not getting into גמרא Gemara
or anything like that is precisely what girls' תורה Torah. education...
ah that's interesting tying it back tying it back to that earlier
discussion because look let's face it the גמרא Gemara which speaks about
תפלות wasn't the other point that I made you know about תורה
שבכתב Torah SheBichtav versus תורה שבעל פה Torah She-baal Peh or sometimes
you know you know when people would teach women they would sort
of if we're going to have to look at a דף of
גמרא Gemara, then we're going to have to xerox it off so
they're not actually handling the גמרא. Gemara You know? Yeah sure oh
totally totally. Yeah and I know some places that you know some
some חרדי Charedi schools are like we're so פרום Frum we don't
even teach the girls
רש"י. Rashi. knowledge that's the dangerous knowledge is the תורה שבעל פה
Torah She-baal Peh, knowledge, but part of it I also think is
that it's power, you know, and that's just knowing like משנה Mishnah
and exactly that because משנה Mishnah and מקרא Mikra do not actually
inform how we act and our real like you know our real
way our actual הלכה halacha the lives תורה שבעל פה, Torah Shebal
Peh it's not as empowering and I think that that's part of
it, you know, but you could also say it's not as intellectually
demanding and the you know fitting in with some of the other
issues that came up about that.
Okay, let's take a look. What was Xerox or מקראות Mikra'ot exactly
the more at the more progressive you know that was the progressive
way to teach גמרא Gemara at the time, of studying גמרא Gemara
that way. Oh really?
As opposed to what? Like just learning it through a כלי שני?
Keli Sheni? Like we can look at learn גמרא Gemara if it's
quoted in like in the ברטנורא Bartenura on the משנה Mishnah or
something? Right, right. The most progressive was that you were allowed to
look at a גמרא Gemara, as long as it was from a
Xerox sheet. Right. Okay, איתמר. itmar. All right, קרא ושנה ולא שימש
תלמידי חכמים. Kara Ve-shana Ve-lo Shimmesh Talmidei Hakhamim. Now that we mentioned
this idea about somebody who learned but did not attend to Torah
sages and that that's a type of a רשע ערום, Rasha Arum,
it's a dangerous type of a person that they go around seeming
very knowledgeable but they really don't have a deep understanding or a
deep sort
of commitment to
what a Torah life is supposed to be. רבי אליעזר אומר הרי
זה עם הארץ. Rabbi Eliezer Omer Harei Zeh Am Ha-aretz. That's like
a commoner. זה הרי פלואי. zeh Horei Polu'i. Now the גמרא Gemara
has a lot of sometimes extremely negative things to say about עמי
הארץ. Amei Ha-aretz. Sometimes it's just that you know a recognition that
the common people the עם הארץ, Am Ha-aretz, the people of the
land, the common people, the farmers, whatever, you know you they can't
be trusted to be as meticulous in certain areas, you know, but
it wasn't always with an antagonism. Different עם הארץ Am Ha-aretz appears
in different ways in different גמרות.
Gemarot. Better than רשע ערום. Rasha Arum.
Right, so but the point is they're normally assumed to be an
עם הארץ Am Ha-aretz is normally right it's better than a רשע
ערום. Rasha Arum. And you may be right, maybe that's a shift
like this person isn't necessarily a רשע rasha you know but they
certainly aren't somebody that you can trust their precise הלכתי halakhic performance,
right? Who knows what their motivation is? Maybe they're a good person
you know they love learning they just don't have the intellectual ability
whatever they're not trying to be who they're not. They're not trying
to represent themselves. Okay, but they're not but the point of עם
הארץ Am Ha-aretz though is obviously עמי הארץ Amei Ha-aretz are also
mostly considered to be uneducated in Rabbinic literature. So the point is
like we shouldn't give any weight to his Rabbinic education. Right, he's
not a רשע ערום Rasha Arum but he's not going to be
necessarily any better in their הלכתי halakhic performance than an uneducated person.
רב נחמני אומר הרי זה בור. Rabbi Nachmani Omer Harei Zeh Bur.
No, he's worse, he's an ignoramus. So בור Bur is actually seen
as worse than an עם הארץ. Am Ha-aretz. An עם הארץ Am
Ha-aretz is somebody who actually more knows the way of the world.
An עם הארץ Am Ha-aretz could have you know a farmer you
know a doctor a lawyer who knows? I mean from the חז"ל
Chazal that could be an עם הארץ Am Ha-aretz just because they're
not part of Rabbinic culture. Okay it doesn't mean that they're not
intelligent or successful. The עמי הארץ Amei Ha-aretz probably are often very
supportive of חז"ל Chazal with their money you know but anyway but
a בור Bur is somebody who's like a complete you know ignoramus
outside of society and so on. So which is really very hard
to understand. תוספות Tosafot tells us like look at one line תוספות
Tosafot תימה כמאן סבירא ליה? Teima Keman Sevira Lei? Like how could
you say that this person is that bad like it's a you
know like he's less he's more ignorant you know maybe again maybe
well somebody who doesn't really understand true knowledge where you know in
any field like somebody who just has a very way of just
like amassing information without understanding it there's an element of that about
being a type of an ignoramus in certain ways you know but
a complete dismissal of information without understanding.
I can imagine,
yes, like in the not knowing much about the culture of the
גמרא, Gemara but like today I can you can you know a
lot of people who are experts in texts and yet not that
doesn't affect their lives, right, in practice.
Right, right, I agree. So I think that that's part of like
the רשע ערום Rasha Arum and the עם הארץ. Am Ha-aretz. That
all makes sense, but the בור Bur is like a real like
you know complete ignoramus. Like so why? I mean maybe it's a
comment about what the value of knowledge is you know knowledge without
understanding is like is ignorance you know but it is a harsh
type of a line. The גמרא Gemara. says but yeah but like
not affecting their lives is I think the עם הארץ Am Ha-aretz
claim. Okay they might not be a רשע Rasha but it doesn't
necessarily make them more observant or anything more careful.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רב
ינאי אומר הרי זה כותי. Rabbi Yannai Omer Harei Zeh Kuti. Samaritan.
Now that's an interesting line because so we think it'd be going
well רש"י Rashi says if you look at רש"י Rashi עם הארץ
Am Ha-aretz רש"י Rashi says שחשוד על המעשרות ועל הטהרות She-hashud Al
Ha-ma'asrot Ve-al Taharot which is because again they're not necessarily scrupulous and
בור Bur רש"י Rashi says is worse and then כותי Kuti רש"י
Rashi says ואסור לאכול פיתו ויינו Ve-assur Le'ekhol Pito Ve-yeno כיון שלא
שימש חכמים אינו מקפיד על דברי חכמים לדעתם Keivan She-lo Shimmesh Hakhamim
Eino Makpid Al Divrei Hakhamim Le-da'atam to know them ולא שנה אלא
להראות עצמו כתלמיד חכמים Ve-lo Shana Ela Le-harot Atzmo Ke-talmid Hakhamim again
back to the רשע ערום. Rasha Arum. But the כותים Kutim are
ones who were really like seen very much a separate sect and
the reason you couldn't drink their wine or eat their bread was
like presumably resulted, like that's like attitudes towards non-Jews to seeing them
as very different, and like not just, not just like you know,
really like a completely almost different sect of you know than the
than the rabbinic Jews or than naturally born Jews. And now it
could just be a concern about again, their observance is so poor,
but I think רש"י Rashi is making a different point. I think
רש"י's Rashi point is not just about the poor observance, but that
part of the whole problem about the Samaritans besides whether they were
as מדקדק במצוות medakdek bemitzvot or which מצוות mitzvot was that they
had a completely
different
authority system. Right, they fundamentally did not submit to or recognize rabbinic
authority. They had a different ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, they had a
completely different understanding of תורה Torah. שבעל פה to the degree that
they had it. They completely just weren't oriented, you know, it's not
like they accepted rabbinic authority but they didn't follow it. You know,
it's that they completely they had a completely different authority system. So
therefore I think that somebody, right, somebody who basically says "I want
to know the text," but is implicitly saying "but I really don't
care what the how the rabbis interpret it," right? "I want to
know it but I completely dismiss like what every, you know, what
the whole rabbinic tradition has to say about this," I think that's
sort of seen as more threatening, you know, to the rabbis. Somebody
who's just ignorant, you know, whether they're fully observant, not fully observant,
they know who the authorities are, they know where the authorities, they
want to listen to us, not want to listen to us, it's
their choice or whatever. Somebody who basically is essentially becoming an authority
unto himself. "Like I'm going to learn these texts and I'm going
to not care what other people have to say about it." Like
who was that? Martin Luther's priesthood of the laity type of a
thing, you know? So I think that's a little bit of what's
going on here.
Know where כותים Cutim were more punctilious in certain things,
in certain areas. So that's what I think he's saying. So that's
what I think the point is, not lack of
punctiliousness, but the basic implicit rejection of the authority system, which is
reflected in the פיתם ויינם pitam veyeinam idea. Okay,
so I think that's רש"י's Rashi point, אינו מקפיד על דברי חכמים
לדעתם. eino makpid al divrei chachamim ladaatan. You don't even want to
know what they are. What do I care what the rabbis have
to say? Okay, so it's in a way it's even more threatening.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, רב אחא בר יעקב אומר
הרי זה מגוס. Rav Acha bar Yaakov omer: harei zeh magus. It's
a magus, it's a mage. Okay, he's a wizard. So what does
that mean? So רש"י Rashi says מכשף ואוחז את העיניים וגונב את
הלבבות. mechachef veochez et haeinayim vegonev et halevavot. Okay, he basically right,
so he's somebody that basically is a what's that word? Illusionist. Right,
not a Zoroastrian?
רש"י Rashi says it's more the mage. He's like cast illusions, he's
a spellcaster.
Okay, he makes people believe that he's so smart, he's casting his
spell on them when he really doesn't, when there's really no substance
behind it, which is sort of like רשע ערום, rasha arum, although
again, makes him much more I don't know somehow wicked than just
being a רשע, rasha, yeah.
In the time of the גמרא gemara it referred to a Persian
priest, mage.
Oh, so maybe that, oh, so it's a Persian category. Oh, so
you don't think it's about illusionist? You think it's like going one
step further than the כותי? Cuti? Like it's again about somebody who
represents almost like a different tradition.
I think רש"י Rashi
might not have known that being in Europe. Okay, well let's keep
on reading cause רש"י's Rashi not is saying it based on a
continuing גמרא, gemara but that's interesting. You're just seeing it as one
step further along the line of כותי Cuti as opposed to the
type of the רשע ערום. rasha arum. And then the mage idea
for רש"י Rashi is about how these רשע ערומים rasha arums cast
their spell and you know deceive people. Okay, but let's take a
look. Okay, מסתברא, mistavra, the גמרא gemara says like
this: אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק מסתברא כרב אחא בר יעקב, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak mistavra keRav Acha bar Yaakov, דאמרי אינשי, deamri
inishi, רטי מגוסא, rati magusa, the magus runs on, ולא ידע מאי
אמר, velo yada mai amar, and he doesn't know what he's saying.
He says his incantations and he doesn't understand them. And similarly, תני
תנא ולא ידע מאי אמר. tani tana velo yada mai amar. Like
you Rabbi Dover said, the idea of the תנא, tana, the memorizer
of the תנאי Tannaitic material, the תנא tana teaches what he's, you
know, what he's memorized and he doesn't know what he's saying. So
they spout out this stuff and for them it's just gobbledygook, they
have no idea what it means. Okay, so that's getting back to
just the that way it's just more emphasizing just the ignorance. Like
it looks like knowledge but it's really a complete ignorance.
Basically as a Saul Lieberman once said, you know, for the what
the rabbis were looking for for the תנאים, Tanna'im, the small 't'
תנאים, Tanna'im, not the רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
תנאים. Tanna'im. The memorizers of the text. He said people with an
excellent memory and very little creativity. So you just wanted them to
be accurate transmitters of the text. You did not want them to
think about it cause then they were going to introduce their own
ideas.
Yes, that's kind of student our educational
system,
that's right, is
for testing like crazy and we are discouraging creativity.
There you go. Okay, תנו רבנן איזהו עם הארץ? tnu rabanan, eizehu
am ha'aretz? Now we're really back. איזהו עם הארץ? eizehu am ha'aretz?
Come on, we just have to talk, memorize. Come on, we just
have to talk, you know, memorize this even if we don't know
what it says. Okay. איזהו עם הארץ? Eizehu am ha'aretz? Okay, what's
an עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? כל שאינו קורא קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית.
Kol she'eino korei krias shema shacharis ve'arvis.
Now we're on the עם הארץ am ha'aretz discussion. So he doesn't
say שמע שחרית וערבית, Shema shacharis ve'arvis, presumably this echoes the גמרא
Gemara in מנחות Menachos that says if somebody would just say קריאת
שמע Krias Shema morning and and evening, הרי זה קיים לא ימוש
ספר התורה הזה מפיך והגית בו יומם ולילה. harei zeh kiyem lo
yamush sefer hatorah hazeh mipicha vehagisa bo yomam valaylah. That if you
just start the day with תורה Torah. and end the day with
תורה, Torah? it frames it as if you're invested in תורה Torah?
the whole day. And an עם הארץ am ha'aretz who doesn't say
שמע שחרית וערבית, Shema shacharis ve'arvis, it's like they're completely outside of
the world of תורה. Torah Again, like you sort of read, you
know, sort of like you think a little bit about like Fiddler
on the Roof? I just watched it recently and there's in the
songs a lot. Anyway, like, you know, with טביה Tevye or whatever,
and he has these very poignant things about, oh, if I could
just have time to sit in the בית כנסת beis knesses and
learn the holy books. He probably hasn't learned one word in his
life, but he understands like what that's about and how he should
want that, you know? And the עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, like, you
don't even learn one line of תורה Torah, at a day. You
don't even say קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית. Krias Shema shacharis ve'arvis. You're
completely like outside of that world.
וברכתה. u'birchasa. וברכתה. u'birchasa. שמע Shema מדרבנן. miderabbanan.
So that was interesting too, right? The extra line of the וברכתה,
u'birchasa, right, exactly. Maybe you do it but you're not part, right,
you're, like the rabbis are the ones that constitute the whole ברכות.
brachos. So how much is it also like about like not sort
of being invested in the rabbinic sort of enterprise? Also the ברכות
brachos of קריאת שמע Krias Shema also very much about, you know,
the ברכות brachos of קריאת שמע Krias Shema double as ברכות התורה.
birchas hatorah. If somebody forgets ברכות התורה birchas hatorah because the ברכות
brachos of קריאת שמע Krias Shema count. Because the ברכות brachos of
קריאת שמע Krias Shema are all about, you know, having chosen us
and giving us, you know, sort of frame the שמע Shema as
a type, the שמע Shema is also a type of תלמוד תורה.
Talmud Torah So I think it's all interconnected. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei
Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim
omrim כל שאינו מניח תפילין. kol she'eino meniach tefillin. If you don't
put on תפילין. tefillin. Now, that's interesting, right? Because now it could
just be somebody's, you know, I don't know, now we're getting less
into knowing of תורה Torah and maybe just not careful in מצוות?
mitzvos? And this is a very basic מצוה. mitzvah. And how could
somebody, if you're at least a little bit into the world of
מצוות, mitzvos, at least you're putting on... I mean, okay, maybe you're
not violating שבת, Shabbos, but you know, the next level a little
bit, you know, daily putting on תפילין tefillin shows a certain level
of participation.
It's actually quite fascinating because we have evidence that in the time
of the ראשונים, Rishonim, there were communities where wearing תפילין tefillin was
very challenged. We always have this very romantic view of how פרום
frum everybody was in the past. יראים Yereim has some of the...
like, I think it's the סמ"ג, Smag, or I think it's the
סמ"ג, Smag, anyway, that he would go town to town and preach
and he would talk to people about how they have to start
wearing תפילין tefillin and putting מזוזות mezuzos on their doors. So, yeah,
but here we're talking about what we believe to have been a
very observant community...
very emblematic of, you know, wrapping, you know, taking the text...
So, thank you very much. So the other possibility, though, is that
תפילין, tefillin, right? You know, the שמע Shema is והיו לאות על
ידך vehayu le'os al yadecha and we're going to get to ולטוטפת
בין עיניך וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך. uletotafos bein einecha uchesavtam al mezuzos
beisecha.
That maybe it's like even if you're not actually learning, but at
least this symbolizes your connection to תורה, Torah, right? Like, even if
you're ודברת בם vedibarta bam and if you're not doing the ודברת
בם, vedibarta bam, there's this symbolic way of speaking about your connection
to תורה. Torah You bind it on your arms, you put it
on your doors. So if they're not even doing that, again, that's
a, you know, a further degree of like remove.
Yeah, you might be... you might have a lot of text knowledge,
but if you don't, you know, wrap it around yourself...
Oh, you haven't internalized it enough. Maybe that's interesting. Although I don't
know if we have evidence that the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz were
to have text knowledge. I don't know. בן עזאי אומר Ben Azzai
omer כל שאין לו ציצית בבגדו. kol she'ein lo tzitzis bevigdo. Okay,
which is again part of the פרשיות parshiyos of תפילין... tefillin... of
קריאת שמע. Krias Shema.
But that does not seem to be directly related again to, you
know, to תורה. Torah But again, it is maybe more related to
this internalizing of your Jewish identity. רבי יונתן בן יוסף אומר Rabbi
Yonasan ben Yosef omer כל שיש לו בנים ואינו מגדלם לתלמוד תורה.
kol sheyesh lo banim ve'eino megadlam letalmud torah. So again, here we're
back to תורה. How strong is your investment in תורה? Are you
investing in your kid's education and making sure that they learn תורה?
Like, maybe you can't, but like, ואינו מגדלם לתלמוד תורה, ve'eino megadlam
letalmud torah, do you sort of see that as something to be
aspiring to, right? It's not just אינו מלמדם תורה, eino melamdam torah,
you're not knowledgeable enough, but have you hired someone? Do you see
that as something to aspire to or not? One minute. אחרים אומרים
Acheirim omrim אפילו קורא ושונה. afilu korei veshoneh.
Now we're back to where we started. Even if you learned and
you מקרא ומשנה mikra u'mishnah ולא שימש תלמידי חכמים, velo shimish talmidei
chachamim, זהו עם הארץ. zehu am ha'aretz.
That's an עם הארץ am ha'aretz because you have knowledge, but again,
it does not lead to character development or does not lead to
true knowledge. קרא ולא שנה. Kara velo shanah. Now here, as opposed
to the earlier statement, which is a... you could even call that
person a בור. boor. No, no, no. בור Boor is less than
that. You know מקרא, mikra, but you don't even know משנה. mishnah.
הרי זה בור. harei zeh boor. Then you're an ignoramus in all
of at least rabbinic discourse. לא קרא ולא שנה. Lo kara velo
shanah. עליו הכתוב אומר Alav hakasuv omer וזרעתי את בית ישראל ואת
בית יהודה זרע אדם וזרע בהמה. vezarati es beis Yisrael ve'es beis
Yehudah zera adam vezera beheimah. I will plant בית
ישראל Beis Yisrael and בית יהודה, Beis Yehudah, the seed of humans
and the seed of animals. Now in the פסוקים, pesukim, that's actually
a ברכה. bracha. It talks about the reflourishing of the society in
the land of Israel. But here it's basically sort of saying
they're
like
animals. so the גבאי gabbai decided to sit him next to the
to the rabbi there by the eastern wall and then he wanted
to try to like show the rabbi like he was a like
he knew something so it was you know
so it was שבת מנחה Shabbos Mincha so they did the צדקתך
Tzidkatcha and צדקתך Tzidkatcha is what is it אדם ובהמה תושיע ה׳
Adam uveheima toshiya Hashem so he so the so he said he's
like well what's the עניין inyan of בהמה beheima אצל etzel אדם
adam so the rabbi says don't ask me the גבאי gabbai was
the one who sat you here.
Yes
anyway
so here we have תפילין tefillin ציצית tzitzis and תלמוד תורה where
does that leave women?
Yeah a very good question. I wish we... there you go back
to exactly thank you for raising that and going back to כל
המלמד בתו תורה right and then you juxtapose it to all of
all of this about what lack of connection to תורה sort of
how that puts somebody places somebody in the rabbi's eyes you know
in society. Okay I do want to say before continuing also this
תוספות קשיא עינא קורא Tosafot kashya ina kora I know we're getting
behind but I can't pass this up so תוספות Tosfos says something
very important he says תימא לרי דאמר פרק הניזקין פרק אם שלחו
איזהו עם הארץ כל שאינו אוכל חולין בטהרה דברי רבי מאיר. Teima
lari de’amar perek Hanizakin perek Im Shelchu eizehu am ha’aretz kol she’eino
ochel chullin betahara divrei Rabbi Meir. Anyway so there's completely different standards
of what's an עם הארץ am ha’aretz in different places and he
says ופירוש דהרבה ענייני עם הארץ הן Upirush deharbei inyanei am ha’aretz
hein עם הארץ am ha’aretz means different things in different places ויש
שאין מקבלים ממנו עדות ve'yesh she’ein mekablin mimenu eidut שיש דהיכא דנאמנין
בעם הארץ מקבלים עדות she-she-heicha deneemanin be’am ha’aretz mekablin eidut etc. etc.
ויש ve'yesh I'm skipping a few lines כשר לעדות ונחשד על הטהרות
ועל המעשרות kasher le’eidut venechshad al hataharot veal hamaasrot או עניין זימון
או עניין שביעית נאמנים בדברים שהם נקנים o inyan zimmun o inyan
shvi’is neemanim bidevarim shehem niknim
so there's all these different הלכות halachot that are said and sometimes
contradictory about עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz and they're really talking about like
different ways of categorizing and defining עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. I have
actually this paper that I started reading that I didn't finish basically
by יאיר פורסטנברג Yair Furstenberg on the status of עם הארץ am
ha'aretz in חז״ל Chazal so you know a lot of
I mean there's been a lot of work on trying to identify
who is it referring to and it's a and it's a term
that goes back to the time of
עזרא Ezra but he basically argues I didn't sort of finish the
paper but he basically argues you know historians have been trying to
identify like who who is it that they're talking about and he
basically tries to argue that they're really not necessarily talking about a
particular identifiable group of people it's more like a concept about like
you know that they're like it's like a like and therefore it
can play different roles under in different contexts in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay let's
continue.
You know you could talk about it in the Orthodox world people
who are not פרום. frum. Right.
What does it mean? Right the whole range. Right so the question
is are there really different groups of people and sometimes it's referring
to group A and sometimes to group B or at a certain
time you know certainly there was a time when it was referring
to a very concrete group but the question is once that concept
becomes part of the rabbinic literature then how much does it continue
always to refer to very concrete groups? Yeah exactly.
Okay ירא ה׳ בני ומלך Yera Hashem beni umelech I
think it is ועם שונים אל תתערב. ve'im shonim al tit'arev.
Fear God and be king and with the שונים shonim do not
mix do not engage yourself do not do not get mixed up
with those שונים. shonim. אמר רבי יצחק אלו ששונים הלכות. Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak elu sheshonim halachot. Those are people that just memorize הלכות halachot
but again have no deep knowledge. Now הלכות halachot would seem better
than משנה Mishnah you're actually learning הלכה halacha. but הלכות halachot here
just does not mean oh you memorized שמירת שבת כהלכתה. Shmiras Shabbos
Kehilchosa. הלכות halachot basically means like you memorize משנה Mishnah okay you
memorize these like what's called these apodictic statements you know without any
discussion about what they mean so again you mislead people okay and
you think that that's הלכה and it's not הלכה. Of course whatever
happened to כל השונה הלכות בכל יום מובטח לו שהוא בן עולם
הבא.
Kol hashoneh halachot bechol yom muvtach lo shehu ben
olam ha-ba. What is it people who talk but don't keep them?
No it's more doesn't understand it and therefore they themselves mislead themselves
and others. So גמרא Gemara says פשיטא peshita obviously what else could
שונים shonim mean of course. No מהו דתימא mahu deteima I might
have thought שונים בחטא shonim be-cheit maybe it means people that constantly
sin and repeatedly sin וכדרב הונא uk’derav Huna like רב הונא Rav
Huna says דאמר רב הונא כיון שעבר אדם עבירה ושנה בה de’amar
Rav Huna keivan she’avar adam aveirah veshana bah once a person does
an עבירה aveirah and then repeats it הותרה לו. hutra lo. So
then it's like it's not even an איסור issur anymore. He's you
learned so many ways of rationalizing what you're doing that it's actually
okay. קמ״ל. kamashma lan. So anyway another גמרא Gemara says הותרה לו
סלקא דעתך hutra lo salka daitach does it really become permitted אלא
אימא נעשית לו כהיתר. ella eima na’aseh lo ke'hetter. And of course
I keep I always tell you whenever we come up to that
that what's his name רב ישראל סלנטר Rav Yisrael Salanter had has
the great like follow-up line he says and once you've done it
three times it's a מצוה. mitzvah. So anyway okay so it could
have meant that repeated sinners but no it means people that just
like mouths off משניות mishnayot okay. Okay where are we תנא התנא
תנאים Tanna Atana Tannaim תנא tana we תנא tana בריתא braisa התנאים
מבלי עולם. Atannaim mevalei olam. Imagine the תנא tanna who had to
memorize this ברייתא. braisa. Okay? The תנאים, tannaim,
the memorizers of משנה, mishna, destroy the world. מבלי עולם סלקא דעתך?
mavlei olam salka daitach? Really? אמר רבינא amar Ravina no. שמורים הלכה
מתוך משנתם. she-morim halacha mitoch mishnasam. There
is not a problem of memorizing the משניות mishnayos as was said.
We need those people to memorize the משנה. mishna. The problem is
that you think you can פסקן pasken based on it. תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, אמר רבי יהושע, amar Rabbi Yehoshua, וכי מבלי
עולם הן? vechi mavlei olam hein? והלא מישבי עולם הן, vehala miyashvei
olam hein, שנאמר הליכות עולם לו, shenemar halichos olam lo, right? You
move, you know, that כל השונה הלכות בכל יום, kol hashoneh halachos
bechol yom, you have to have this memorized. That's the foundation on
which all the Talmudic discussion is built. אלא שמורים הלכה מתוך משנתם.
ela she-morim halacha mitoch mishnasam. The problem is not memorizing. The problem
is then thinking you can פסקן pasken based on it. Yes.
We have רבינא Ravina and רבי יהושע who
lived centuries apart arguing.
What can I tell you?
אשה פרושה. isha perushah. Now, a woman who separates herself, again meaning
like shows that she's like, you know, interested in not having physical
pleasure, whatever. She's one of the מבלי עולם, mavlei olam, destroyers of
the world, because again there's skepticism. Yeah, yeah, that's the way she
presents. What's she really doing? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara adds
to this. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, בתולה צליינית, besulah tzalya-nis,
a praying virgin, ואלמנה שובבית, ve-almanah shovevis,
and a wandering widow, וקטן שלא כלו חדשיו, vekatan shelo kalu chodashav,
and a minor who does not, whose months have not been complete,
which probably means a boy that was born like in his eighth
month is what it would normally mean. הרי אלו מבלי עולם. harei
elu mavlei olam. They destroy the world. Who are these people? So
רש"י Rashi says the בתולה צליינית besulah tzalya-nis
is somebody that's like, you know, always דאוונינג davening and praying and
so on. So what's the matter with her? So again תוספות Tosafot
sort of says it's sort of like what we said before, that
she looks very פרום frum but who knows? And she looks like,
oh my god, this virginal person and she's always praying, she's so
פרום. frum. What's she really doing? Like, you know, it's sort of
like the אשה פרושה. isha perushah.
Asceticism? What? Asceticism. Asceticism. Yeah, right. So and the אלמנה שובבית ve-almanah
shovevis is the widow who's constantly going around the community and visiting
all of her friends all the time. Maybe she doesn't have a
husband to keep her home and to keep her busy. And basically
her concern is that she's like a gossip. At least that's the
way רש"י Rashi says it. Of course, then it wouldn't really exactly
fit the model because it wouldn't be somebody who's presenting as somebody
that they're not. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay.
Let me guess, a woman
who like, you know, oh let's go visit the this and that
and the, but they're not visiting to help people out, they're just
visiting to.
Oh, that's interesting. I'm visiting, I care about them, I want to
see how they're doing. That's a nice point. Okay, so anyway, קטן
שלא כלו חדשיו katan shelo kalu chodashav is not clear, the גמרא
Gemara will get to it. Let's see. איני? eini? Is this true?
ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan, למדנו יראת חטא מבתולה, lamadnu yiras
cheit mibesulah, we can learn fear of sin from the young lady
and from a, you know, from a young woman, וקיבול שכר מאלמנה,
ve-kibul sachar mei-almanah, and what the reward means from the following story
about the widow. יראת חטא מבתולה, yiras cheit mibesulah, what's that story?
דרבי יוחנן שמע לה לההיא בתולה, de-Rabbi Yochanan shama lah le-hahi besulah,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan heard this, you know, young virgin woman, דנפלה
אפי', de-nafla apei, she fell down on the ground like נפילת אפים
nefilas apayim and prayed to God, ואמרה, ve-amra, רבונו של עולם, ribbono
shel olam, Master of the Universe, בראת גן עדן ובראת גיהנום, baras
Gan Eden u-varas Gehennom, you've created, you know, paradise and גיהנום, Gehennom,
בראת צדיקים בראת רשעים, baras tzaddikim baras reshaim, righteous and wicked people,
יהי רצון מלפניך שלא יכשלו בי בני אדם. yehi ratzon milfanecha shelo
yikashlu bi bnei adam. May it be Your will that people don't
sin by me, that I don't lead, you know, men astray. Now,
that's pretty interesting in terms of יראת חטא. yiras cheit. Like, you
know, first of all, like why יראת חטא yiras cheit you would
think is may it be Your will that I don't go astray,
you know? So, oh look how פרום frum she is. It's not
just that she doesn't want to go astray, she doesn't want even
to be the cause for somebody else to go astray. On the
one hand, okay, that's lovely. Like, you know, it's sort of like
the תפילה tefillah you say before you go into the בית המדרש,
beis hamidrash, you know, שלא יכשלו, shelo yikashlu, you know, my colleagues
shouldn't be נכשל nichshal in anything I say. I shouldn't, I'm so
afraid of sin, I'm afraid that unintentionally, without my intention, I might
accidentally cause somebody else to unintentionally sin. Okay, but it's a very
big problem in terms of the whole issue about, you know, women
as sex objects and internalizing for themselves, you know, sort of like
the male gaze and the male lust and that's their responsibility. I
mean, I've got a lot to say about that and that's obviously,
you know, very, very deeply, deeply problematic. So, and also, you know,
ties into all of מסכת סוטה. Maseches Sotah. So there's like a
lot of things going on here beyond just יראת חטא. yiras cheit.
And in terms of anyway, did you want to say something, Jenna?
No? Okay. I thought I saw, I thought I saw you say
something. I'm not, I don't want to put you on the spot.
I thought I saw some...
Okay, so this is the question, because then what's the problem? This
seems to be a good point.
All right, all right. We're still, so how could you say there's
a problem with the בתולה besulah and the אלמנה? almanah? Look how
פרום frum they are, or look how sometimes it's genuine פרום-קייט. frum-keit.
Now, what's the אלמנה? almanah? So וקיבול שכר מאלמנה, ve-kibul sachar mei-almanah,
where are we? וקיבול שכר מאלמנה, ve-kibul sachar mei-almanah, דהיא אלמנה, de-hi
almanah, a certain widow, דהוה בי כנישתא בשיבבותה,
de-hava bei knishta be-shivvuseih, that there was a synagogue in her, in
her community. וכל יומא הוה אתיא ומצלי בבי מדרשא דרבי יוחנן. ve-chol
yoma hava asya u-matzli be-bei midrasha de-Rabbi Yochanan.
And every day though she wouldn't go to the בית הכנסת, beis
haknesseth, she'd come and דאוון daven in רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's בית
המדרש. beis hamidrash. Again, it's רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, which is interesting.
אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her, בתי, biti, לא בית
הכנסת בשיבבותיך? lo beis haknesseth be-shivvuseich?
isn't there a synagogue in your community? Why are you coming to
the בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? אמרה לו Amrah lo she said to
him רבי לא שכר פסיעות יש לי lo sechar psios yesh li
don't I get the merit of doing this extra walking, to do
this schlepping out and coming to the בית המדרש? Beis HaMedrash? So
that's how you see that as we learn קיבול שכר. kibul sechar.
Now of course it's very funny like it seems like almost frivolous.
Like what's the point of walking longer if you don't have to
walk longer? Like you know now what you could say is that
no you learn actually you train yourself for this idea of you
know exerting the extra effort to go ahead and to do מצוות
mitzvos so even though here the extra effort wasn't needed you know
you're internalizing this type of a character about like I'm prepared to
you know if I had to go five miles to get to
שול shul I would go and I'm going to train myself to
do that. But both of these cases are themselves like very problematic.
They're being held up as these ideals, right? And again like it's
like you know they're almost like extremes that are silly extremes. Like
יראת חטא yiras cheit starts with concerning yourself about your own sin,
forget even the whole sex
sex object issue. יראת חטא yiras cheit starts with concerning yourself about
your own ממזירות. mamzeirus. Oh, but look how far they went. You
know, extending yourself for מצוות mitzvos it starts with when it's really
necessary. So again, bringing an example of people doing it in an
excessive way I'm not so sure is necessarily a helpful example since
we could be questioning whether it's really even appropriate in this type
of a circumstance. Yes.
Is it better to pray in a בית כנסת Beis Knesset or
בית מדרש? Beis Medrash?
Ah, so that could be an interesting question too, right? And like
you know and maybe is this also showing the fact that she
has a she wants to connect to the world of תורה, going
back to the whole issue about women and תורה and so on.
Like maybe that is why she's extending herself because she wants to
connect more to the world of תורה, not just the world of
תפילה. tefillah. But anyway.
More time leaving and hanging out in the bathroom?
Oh, maybe that's the problem. Okay. So right, maybe also there's probably
not as much but there probably isn't as much socializing in the
בית מדרש Beis Medrash as in the בית כנסת. Beis Knesset. So
maybe that's also part of the point, like you know that there
I'm serious, so you know here they are sort of so so
that would help explain why this is an important thing.
Is the example related to אלו הם מבלי עולם? elu hem mavlei
olam?
Yes, so that's the question. How could you say widows and virgins
are מבלי עולם? mavlei olam? Look at these righteous ones. Okay. So
the גמרא says now of course the question is are we saying
all widows and all virgins, maybe it was depends on how they're
acting. So anyway the גמרא says no. כי קאמר, ki ka'amar, so
it's going to say yeah there are different types. Who what type
of widows are we talking about? כגון יוחני בת רטיבי kegon Yochni
bat Retivi like this woman Yochni bat Retivi. Now that answers it.
So רש"י Rashi says and I don't know who tells רש"י Rashi
what the story is, but רש"י Rashi says that the that the
that the story was was that this was again a witch or
somebody who did you know incantations and she she made her
פרנסה parnassa as a midwife. So she basically did did some incantations
that the woman wouldn't be able to give birth and then she
was called on to help them and then she reversed the incantations
so that and then she was able to like get her a
big reputation and everybody needed her services and the whole thing and
then one day she was found out. So eh like I have
no idea where רש"י Rashi got that story from. Okay that happens
sometimes that רש"י Rashi gives you like a whole אגדתא Aggadata backdrop
and like it's not in other rabbinic literature, you know, must have
been some מסורה messorah to explain what this was. But again like
what does how does that tie in to widows who are traveling
widows? Like you know the traveling widows was a nice simple explanation.
Like Michael said, you know, going around and saying oh I just
want to see how this person is doing and I want to
pay a call and you're really just a big gossip, you know?
Anyway I I don't know. Moving on. Okay. מאי קטן שלא כלו
לו חדשיו? mai katan shelo kalu lo chodashav? What's a קטן katan
whose months have not been complete? So הכא תרגימו hacha targimu here
in בבל Bavel they explained it זה תלמיד חכם המבעט ברבותיו. zeh
talmid chacham hamiva'eit berabbotav. Somebody who's like young and is like you
know thinks that they're what is it bigger you know bigger than
their breeches? Yeah like you know thinks that they're you know that
that that they're you know you know it's disrespectful of their רבות
rabbos and of people of greater age and authority and they just
so think they're a little bit metaphorical, they're a little too taken
by
themselves. You know actually תוספות Tosafot. quotes a ירושלמי if you look
about ten lines up right after the print end of the parentheses
in תוספות. Tosafot רבי חלקיא בשם רבי סימון, Rabbi Chilkiya beshem Rabbi
Simon, זה שהוא גדול בתורה שלא בפרקו, zeh shehu gadol baTorah shelo
befirko,
somebody who actually is beyond their years in terms of their תורה
knowledge, ומבזה את הגדולים ממנו, umevazeh et hagedolim mimenu, and therefore they
think that they can denigrate you know people that are you know
older and more you know and more תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim because
they're so impressed with how brilliant they are. Sadly this is a
phenomenon that we see when kids come back from a year in
Israel. I'm serious. They all of a sudden now they're the world's
biggest תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, they know everything, you know, their community
רבי you know is completely like garbage in their eyes. Anyway so
that's קטן שלא כלו לו
חדשיו.
katan shelo kalu
lo chodashav.
How did you say תרגימו?
targimu? We we've translated it, that this is how we interpret it.
ואבא אמר v'Abba amar oh I like the
I should like the second explanation. Right right there's the גמרא says
ואבא אמר. v'Abba amar.
Yeah here here in בבל Bavel we explained it in the following
way. And until I don't see another opinion.
I know well
we're
going to get to it. Yeah the next one is in תוספות
we don't have that one anyway. רבי אבא אמר זה תלמיד שלא
הגיע להוראה. Rabbi Abba amar zeh talmid shelo higia lehora'ah.
Now it's not about their relationship to other great, other rabbis, but
it is about their effect on other people, that they actually think
that they are ready to פסקן pasken and they're פסקנינג paskening and
they're not ready. And that's really מבלי עולם mavlai olam because it's
leading people astray. And you know, sometimes this might not be just
because they don't have enough knowledge. Maybe they are brilliant, but פסקנינג
paskening requires like wisdom. It requires like knowing, you know, people and
knowing the world and it doesn't just require like book knowledge. דאמר
רבי אבהו אמר רב הונא אמר רב, D'amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rav
Huna amar Rav, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the verse
כי רבים חללים הפילה? ki rabim chalalim hipila? This is again, interestingly,
a פסוק pasuk about a woman who is like a, you know,
a seductress woman, as so again in the context of סוטה, but
now it's about the about we'll see what it means because many,
you know, masses she did she sort of, you know, caused to
fall, ועצומים כל הרוגיה, v'atzumim kol harugeha,
and great many are all those that she murdered. כי רבים חללים
הפילה, Ki rabim chalalim hipila, what's רבים חללים הפילה? rabim chalalim hipila?
זה תלמיד חכם שלא הגיע להוראה ומורה. Zeh talmid chacham shelo higia
l'horah u'moreh. He has he's not yet fit for פסקנינג paskening and
רש"י Rashi says it's a play on the word הפילה hipila which
is a נפל, nefel, which is like קטן שלא כלו לו חדשיו,
katan shelo chalu lo chadashav, right, a child born an infant born
before its time is going to be like almost a נפל, nefel,
a mis, you know, a miscarriage. It's a miscarriage of justice. Anyway,
so they're murdering people, they're פסקנינג paskening and leading people astray. ועצומים
כל הרוגיה, V'atzumim kol harugeha, great are all those that she slaughtered.
זה תלמיד חכם שהגיע להוראה ואינו מורה. Zeh talmid chacham shehigia l'horah
v'eino moreh. It's the opposite. If you're should be פסקנינג paskening and
you're not, so you're not helping people who need your help, maybe
you're leaving the field open for people who need who shouldn't be
playing that role, and you're also doing a terrible things by not
פסקנינג. paskening. So here רש"י Rashi says it's a play on the
word עצומים atzumim to be עוצם עיניו, otzem einav, close your eyes,
like you know, that you're you're not doing what you need to
be doing, you're closing your eyes to what to what's demands of
you. Or to just be as the מהרש"א Maharsha says עצומים, atzumim,
no, you're עצום, atzum, you're great, you're fit for this and you're
not doing it. So it's better, you know, it's equal if you're
acting when you shouldn't and if you're not acting when you should.
Very beautiful in רב משה פיינשטיין'ס Rav Moshe Feinstein's introduction to the
אגרות משה, Igros Moshe, he says that when like he says he
was hesitant to פסקן pasken because he said like who am I
to פסקן pasken and let's say I פסקן pasken incorrectly, you know?
And the גמרא says you know, זה תלמיד שלא הגיע להוראה ומורה,
zeh talmid shelo higia l'horah u'moreh, it says you know, רבים חללים
הפילה. rabim chalalim hipila. But then רב משה Rav Moshe said, but
then I couldn't not פסקן pasken because the next line says עצומים
כל הרוגיה, atzumim kol harugeha, like if you're הגיע להוראה ואינו מורה.
higia l'horah v'eino moreh. It's like, you know, you can't sort of
shirk your responsibility, you have to do it like you know, when
when you are fit. The other interesting thing by the way to
mention about all of this is notice here not just did we
transform a פסוק pasuk about a seductress woman and make it about
men, but you know, we started with a משנה mishna about a
woman who is suspected of a סוטה and maybe she actually committed
it but she's getting away with it because she has זכות zchus
and maybe we shouldn't teach her תורה because the זכות will she'll
figure out a loophole so she'll present herself, you know, she'll figure
out how to get away with what she's doing and present herself
one way and be in another way, and by this stage we've
totally forgotten about the woman. And we've like focused on this very
broad societal phenomenon that expresses itself in many ways among men and
women. I mean you have the אמנה amana but it's many different
ways about people who basically present themselves as something that they're not.
You know, so I think that there's again something powerful by not
by not keeping this hyper-focused on the evil seductress women that are,
you know, it's like oh there are a lot of people like
this in many different ways and we have to be aware of
this phenomenon. Okay, and then the גמרא just ends this point one
minute. ועד כמה, ארבעים שנים? V'ad kamah, arbaim shanim? Ad to what
stage are you supposed to wait until פסקנינג? paskening? 40 years. איני?
Aini? והא רבה אורי, V'ha Rabbah ori, רבה Rabbah פסקנד paskened and
he only lived till 40? So the גמרא says בשווי. B'shavi. No,
that's only all other things being equal. So there's actually an interesting
debate of רש"י Rashi and תוס' Tosfos how to read that. רש"י
Rashi reads that that if you're equivalent to the פוסקים poskim that
are around, then even if you're less than 40 you can פסקן.
pasken. You only can't פסקן pasken if you're less than 40 if
you're less than the פוסקים poskim that are around. תוס' Tosfos says
no, no, no. If you're equivalent you can't פסקן pasken until you're
40. But if you're but if you're better than everyone around, then
even if you're under 40 you can פסקן. pasken. So it's a
difference about whether you have to be equal or better. The issue
of 40 years is also interesting. תוס' Tosfos says it's not that
you have to be 40 years old. What difference is 40 years
old going to make although you could say it's about 40 years
of learning is what תוס' Tosfos says, which is oh my god
then how old do you have to be? But you could understand
40 years old again getting to this point that it's not just
about book knowledge, it's about life experience and so on. And then
the issue becomes nowadays that you know, that so a lot of
that is because you had to just memorize and learn so much
material and therefore before you could actually פסקן pasken you needed to
invest a lot of years in just getting all that information into
you. Nowadays that all the information is available in books, you know,
the פוסקים poskim say that some of these issues change radically in
those types of cases. Let's just try to read quickly a little
bit more because we're we've fallen behind. ומכות פרושים, U'makkot perushim, and
the last one that's bad is the the the smitings of the
of the aesthetics. Although interestingly פרושים perushim is also Pharisees. But anyway,
it means again the According to רש"י Rashi people who self-flagellate and
look so פרום frum but again they miss out what real righteousness
is about but they present themselves that way maybe they've also even
tricked themselves in terms of what righteousness is about. תנו רבנן Tanu
Rabbanan שבעה פרושים הם shiva prushim heim there are seven that are
פרושים Prushim that are not good. פרוש שכמי Parush Shichmi פרוש ניקפי
Parush Nikpi פרוש קיזאי Parush Kizai פרוש מדוכיא Parush Meduchya פרוש מה
חובתי ואעשנה Parush Machovasi V’eesenu פרוש מאהבה Parush Mei'ahava פרוש מיראה. Prosh
Mi’yira. Now we’re going to explain them. פרוש שכמי Parush Shichmi the
פרוש Parush of שכמי Shichmi זה עושה מעשה שכם zeh oseh ma'aseh
Shechem the doings of שכם. Shechem. What does that
mean? רש"י Rashi says coming up in the פרשה parsha that they
all did ברית מילה brit milah but they weren't doing it for
the right reason. So it's somebody that basically
takes their does certain behaviors but not for the right reason. The
מהרש"א Maharsha said I don't understand מתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה mitoch
shelo lishma ba lishma what was so terrible? Not what שכם Shechem
did but what the people of the town did what was so
terrible? So he said no what was terrible was that first again
going back to שכם Shechem first he raped and then he decided
to do the ברית מילה brit milah that’s not exactly if you
first
if you're already a רשע rasha and then you're doing this to
cover it up and to make yourself present yourself in a particular
way that's a bit of a problem. Okay what's פרוש ניקפי? prosh
nikpi? זה המנקף את רגליו Zeh hamenakeif es raglav that you bang
your legs. רש"י Rashi says it means you walk very daintily to
show
how humble you are or righteous you are or something but obviously
it's all a show. פרוש קיזאי Prosh Kizai
so what does that mean? קיזאי Kizai is to let blood. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak זה המקיז דם
לכתלים. Zeh hamakiz dam lektalin. You bang into walls and you cause
yourself to bleed. רש"י Rashi says
exactly. רש"י Rashi says you’re too פרום frum to look at a
woman so you’re banging into walls. Although I do have to tell
you I don't know if I should tell you this I'm not
trying to I don't know if this is going to be showing
off or embarrassing myself but anyway when I was a teenager I
was at a stage that I was so פרום frum about not
looking at women that I was constantly as I was walking trying
to חזר chazar the stuff that I was learning in the that
I learned that I was learning in ישיבה yeshiva that I would
have my eyes closed I was חזר'ינג chazaring I would literally walk
into telephone poles. So anyway. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak that’ll go in the unauthorized biography. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak okay what exactly exactly. פרוש
מדוכיא Prosh Meduchya so what’s פרוש מדוכיא? Prosh Meduchya? What does that
mean? מדוכיא Meduchya is a pestle the thing you use to bang
whatever spices. So what’s that? אמר רבה בר שילה Amar Rabbah bar
Shila דמשפי כמדוכיא demishapei k'meduchya you’re so bent down the curve of
this of the pestle you’re showing yourself humble but again it’s all
a show. פרוש מה חובתי ואעשנה Prosh machovasi ve’esenu tell me what
my responsibility is and I'll do it. גמרא says what do you
mean? מעליותא היא Ma’alyusa hi that’s great tell me what I need
to do and I'll do it. אלא דאמר Ela de'amar no no
מה חובתי תו ואעשנה Machovasi tu ve’esenu I’ve done everything I need
to do if you tell me whatever else I haven't done and
I'll take care of it but you start by presenting yourself as
I've done all my responsibilities tell me anything I haven't done and
I'll do it but you present yourself like you’ve already done everything
and again that’s a problem. Now פרוש מאהבה prosh mei'ahava פרוש מיראה
prosh mi’yira what’s that? That sounds פרום. frum. אמר ליה אביי ורבא
לתנא amar lei Abaye ve'Rava letana הא לא תתני ha lo tisni
פרוש מאהבה prosh mei'ahava פרוש מיראה. prosh mi’yira.
Don't teach that. That's not a bad thing even if the אהבה
ahava and יראה yira is the wrong אהבה ahava and יראה. yira.
What's the wrong אהבה ahava and יראה? yira? דאמר רב יהודה אמר
רב De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav לעולם יעסוק אדם בתורה ובמצוות אף
על פי שלא לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה. Le'olam ya'asok adam
b'Torah u'v'mitzvot af al pi shelo lishma, shemitoch shelo lishma ba lishma.
So the אהבה ahava and יראה yira is you do it because
of love of reward or fear of punishment but even if it's
that's a bad motivation
it’s not intrinsically problematic ultimately it מביא לעולם mavi le'olam it’ll ultimately
lead to good behavior. The problem of everybody else was that they
were presenting themselves as something they weren't. Here okay it’s just motivation
the motivation could ultimately lead to something good. אמר רב לעולם יעסוק
Amar Rav le'olam ya'asok we just said that. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak דמטמרא מטמרא ודמגליא מגליא. Demitamera mitamera,
demigalya migalya.
What's hidden is hidden what's revealed is revealed. Meaning here we just
got through explaining that there are all these people that present themselves
like who they’re not. So it's not a fair world what are
you supposed to do about that? Everybody presents themselves as so פרום.
frum. So it says look we know what we know. We can
what's hidden is hidden we won't know it what's revealed is revealed
we have to do the best we can. בי דינא רבה ליפרע
מהני דחפו גונדי. Beis dina rabba le’iparei mehani dechafu gundei. The ultimate
the high court God will ultimately mete out justice to those that
wrapped themselves in a טלית tallit that look פרום frum and that
they're not
really
פרום. frum. אמר ליה ינאי מלכא לדביתיה Amar lei Yannai Malka l'devasei
last thing ינאי Yannai the king says to his wife because ינאי
Yannai killed a lot of the sages and his wife was going
to be afraid of payback. אל תתיראי מן הפרושים. Al tishari min
ha’Prushim.
Now the פרושים Prushim here actually mean the Pharisees. Don't fear from
the פרושים Prushim ולא ממי שאינם פרושים v'lo mi'mi she'einam Prushim
not from those that aren't. The פרושים Prushim are righteous they're not
going to do anything to you even though we did this evil
to them and the non-Pharisees they are our friends so those are
not the people you have to be aware of or just in
general don't be afraid from people that are genuinely פרום frum or
people that are genuinely not פרום. frum. from the people to be
afraid of. אלא מן הצבועין. Ela min hatzevu'in. You have to be
afraid from like the chameleons, from the people that present themselves one
way and are really in another way, שדומין לפרושים, she'domin la'Prushim, they
seem like ascetics and Pharisees and פרום, frum, שמעשיהם מעשה זמרי she'ma'aseihem
ma'aseh Zimri ומבקשים שכר כפנחס. u'mevakshim sachar k'Pinchas.
That is such a great line. There are so many people like
that. They go out and they act like זמרי, Zimri, you know,
they go out and they sleep around with whatever women or whatever
violations, and they think that they're righteous, and they present themselves like
they deserve שכר as if they're a פנחס. Pinchas.
All right, and with that we've